Guide to the Board of Trustees records, 1821-2003 RG0001
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
- Committees, 1911-1960; RG0001 Series 5; 4 Linear feet (Box 1, Box 2, Box 3, Box 4, Box 5, Box 6, Box 7, Box 8)
  - Executive Committee--correspondence and meeting minutes, 05/04/1959 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    Text on folder "Chairman Fleming withdrew his name from consideration for the Chairmanship of the Board. Letter from Acting President Colclough to Chairman Fleming considered. Resolution to honor Chairman Fleming approved by the Committees. Trustee Ellison was named as nominee for office of the Chairman; Trustee E.K. Morris and Trustee Godfrey Munter were named to fill offices of Secretary and Assistant Secretary; it was suggested that Trustee Strong be asked if he would allow his name to be recommended to the Board for the office of Vice Chairman. Acting President Colclough advised the Committees that a new HUMRRO contract had been concluded and a contract signed at a fixed fee of $220,000. The members of the Special Committee to Consider the Future Leadership of the University agreed to meet for luncheon on May 14, 1959."
  - Executive Committee--correspondence and meeting minutes, 02/11/1958 (Box 2, Folder 50)
    Text on folder "The Committee approved the conferring of degrees on February 22 upon the candidates listed in the enclosed galley which have been approved by their respective faculties as meeting all requirements for their degrees."
  - Executive Committee--correspondence and meeting minutes, 04/30/1957 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Executive Committee--correspondence and meeting minutes, 02/21/1957 (Box 2, Folder 52)
    Text on folder "Presentation by Trustee Lawson, Chairman of Committee on Buildings and Lands, of opinion and resolutions prepared by University Counsel in regard to purchase of property in Square 40 owned by President Marvin and Miss Sedgwick. Committee voted to recommend to the Board the purchase of the properties in Square 40 on the basis of the audit by Lybrand, Ross Bros. & Montgomery. Suggestion of an appropriate resolution and perhaps emeritus status for the Deans who are retiring."
  - Executive Committee--correspondence and meeting minutes, 12/27/1956 (Box 2, Folder 53)
    Text on folder "Approval of purchase of Lots 11-17 in Square 57, 614-626 22nd Street, N.W. Proposal to relacate [relocate] the freeway to pass through squares not now owned by Unv. (Squares 40, 41, and 42). Committees voted to: 1. Have a brief prepared with help of legal counsel. 2. Appoint a committee to make appropriate contacts on this matter."
  - Executive Committee--correspondence and meeting minutes, 10/23/1956 (Box 2, Folder 54)
    Text on folder "A quorum not present. Re: Purchase of Lot 827 in Square 122, s.e. corner of 19th and F Streets, N.W. owned by Church Orphanage Assn. of St. John's Church. Trustee Tompkins had recommended that the University offer $400,000 for this property. Since no quorum was present, the Committee counseled the president to see what action could be taken regarding purchase. Re: 2 properties in Square 119. No action or recommendation."
  - Executive Committee--correspondence and meeting minutes, 07/17/1956 (Box 2, Folder 55)
    Text on folder "Committee confirmed action of the Committee on Buildings and Lands approving the employment of Mr. Henry S. Churchill and the firm of Wheelwright, Stevenson, Langran, & Fanning as professional assistance for the development of the University plan as part of the redevelopment program."
  - Executive Committee--correspondence and meeting minutes, 07/03/1956 (Box 2, Folder 56)
    Text on folder "Ratified action relative to purchase of 804 22nd Street, N.W. (Lot 801 in Square 55) for $16,500.00. Voted to purchase Marion Apt. House, 2000 H Street, N.W. (Lot 39 in Square 102) at price not to exceed $140,000. To negotiate with seller. Proposed Wing to Tompkins Hall of Engineering. To go over sketches with Trustee Tompkins and to take up possibility of extending line of credit, if necessary, at Riggs Bank. New Zoning regulations for District. To be discussed at later meeting. Presentation of statement by Attorney Hugh Obear relative to property owned by President Marin [President Marvin?] in Square 40. Committee was appointed to work out proper basis for acquiring the property."
  - Executive Committee--correspondence and meeting minutes, 06/29/1954 (Box 2, Folder 57)
    Text on folder "Authority to purchase Lot 51 in Square 101, 2023 H Street, N.W. Discussion regarding desirability of purchasing Lots 14, 16, 18, and 822 in Square 56 to complete area for Tomkins Engineering Building. Discussion of policy in reference to admissions. Merger Agreement between National University and The George Washington University."
  - Executive Committee--correspondence and meeting minutes, 02/12/1953 (Box 2, Folder 58)
    Text on folder "Approval of reorganization of University's administration: Appointment of: Dean of Faculties, Appointment of: Comptroller and Treasurer."
  - Executive Committee--correspondence and meeting minutes, 05/14/1952 (Box 2, Folder 59)
    Text on folder "Payment to full-time members of the Staff. Mr. Van Devanter named Chairman of Special Gifts Committee."
  - Executive Committee--correspondence and meeting minutes, 02/04/1949 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Executive Committee--correspondence and meeting minutes, 12/17/1946 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Executive Committee--correspondence and meeting minutes, 10/14/1946 (Box 2, Folder 62)
    Text on folder "Discussion of non-admission of negroes to Lisner Auditorium."
  - Executive Committee--correspondence and meeting minutes, 06/18/1946 (Box 2, Folder 63)
    mnjhg
    Text on folder "Hospital Fund Drive"
  - Executive Committee--correspondence and meeting minutes, 02/04/1946 (Box 2, Folder 64)
    Text on folder "Increase in tuition fee - $8 to $10 per credit hour, effective September 1, 1946. Consideration of need for new classroom building. Establishment of new teaching posts as of 2/1/46 to care for increased enrollment. Purchase of Lot B in Square 80, Lots 21, 829, and 830 in Square 101 - borrowing of $60,000 on latter property. Employment of John Price Jones Corporation to make preliminary survey looking towards Law School & Hospital drives. 125th anniversary publication authorized. Resumption of intercollegiate athletics; appointment of Max Farrington as Director of Activities for Men."
  - Executive Committee--correspondence and meeting minutes, 07/19/1945 (Box 2, Folder 65)
    Text on folder "Consideration of retirement plan. Gifts to new hospital: Bernard Baruch and Mrs. Frances Watson. Financial status of the hospital project. Consideration of request from alumnus for change of name on diploma. Establishment of scholarship by Louisa A. Kroll. Association of American Junior Colleges' request for office space. Kellogg Foundation funds for research program in School of Medicine. Death of Trustee Reichelderfer. Faculty resignations."
  - Executive Committee--correspondence and meeting minutes, 07/17/1945 (Box 2, Folder 66)
    Text on folder "Presentation by President Marvin of charts showing development of GWU since 1927. Summary of budget for 1945-46. Report of the Committee on Buildings and Lands. Suggested method of meeting cost of extensive real estate purchases. Property purchases considered desirable at this time. (Committee recessed to meet on 19 July 1945)"
  - Executive Committee--correspondence and meeting minutes, 06/13/1945 (Box 2, Folder 67)
    Text on folder "Time of summer meetings 12 noon 2d Tuesday in July and August. Cost of equipment of new hospital. Discussion of campaign to raise funds for new hospital. Use of the Auditorium by the Navy Department. Commendation of the Report of the Comptroller for year ending 8/31/44. Retirement plan for staff. Discussion of attitude of college students in general."
  - Executive Committee--correspondence and meeting minutes, 05/11/1945 (Box 2, Folder 68)
    Text on folder "Government contracts - termination of ESMWT as of 6/30/45. Property to be purchased - Lot 823, Square 40, 932 23 St. Lot 34, Square 79, 731 22nd St. Lots 34, 35, 822, 823, 824, Square 41, Eye St. between 23d & 24th. Consideration of plan whereby friends of University would invest in real estate for the University. Honorary degrees to be conferred at convocation of 5/30/45. Portraits of the presidents of the University."
  - Executive Committee--correspondence and meeting minutes, 04/11/1945 (Box 2, Folder 69)
    Text on folder "FWA; problem in condemnation of property of the Reverend Patrick Murphy in Square 54. Authorization of the President to offer invalid lady accommodations in a ward of GWU Hospital. Authorization of the President to offer Father Murphy rental of a University property. Increased interest in building projects brought about by the new hospital building. Building for Law School and Law Library. Need of accommodations for physicians' parking near hospital. Need of accomodations for physicians' offices. Revision of Faculty Code--amendment by 2/3 vote rather than majority."
  - Executive Committee--correspondence and meeting minutes, 02/06/1945 (Box 2, Folder 70)
    Text on folder "Retirement of George Byron Roth as Professor Emeritus of Pharmacology. Authorization of the President to confer degrees at Winter Convocation of February 22, 1945. Establishment of new post - Superintendent of the Hospital. Appointment of Leo G. Schmelzer as Superintendent of the Hospital."
  - Executive Committee--correspondence and meeting minutes, 10/10/1944 (Box 2, Folder 71)
    Text on folder "Increase in enrollment and student charges. Progress in remodelling of warehouse for stores department. Progress in remodelling of Houck properties for use of research projects in Pharmacy. Transfer of Junior and Columbian College offices from Building C to Building D. Leasing of Square 56 to Federal Works Agency for week-end housing of servicemen. Hospital project. Selection of Faulkner & Kingsbury as architects and of the Charles H. Tompkins Company as builder. Maintenance of close cooperation between medical school & hospital through appointment of an assistant dean of School of Med. Discussion of method of meeting 1910 indebtedness and of financing hospital. Protest of St. Paul's Episcopal Church against condemnation of Square 54, site of the purposed hospital. Authorization of President to prepare a resolution for presentation to the Board of Trustees on October 12 empowering the President to sign contract with Federal Works Agency."
  - Executive Committee--meeting minutes, 08/22/1944 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Text on folder "Bequests of Wilmer Worth and Harry C. Davis. Proposed transfer of money held in trust for American School of Classical Studies at Athens. Authorization of request for alcohol permit for Allegany Ballistics Laboratory. President Marvin's relationship to the Hospital Presidents' Association of the District of Columbia. Discussion of hospital contract with Federal Works Agency-- suggestion as to how 1910 indebtedness might be removed-- authorization for preparation of new application for hospital to Federal Works Agency."
  - Executive Committee--meeting minutes, 06/08/1944 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Text on folder "Hospital project"
  - Executive Committee--meeting minutes, 04/20/1944 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Text on folder "University contracts with the Government Hospital project"
  - Executive Committee--meeting minutes, 03/16/1944 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    Text on folder "Robbery at Strong Hall. Junior college proposal by Washington Board of Trade. Hospital plans."
  - Executive Committee--meeting minutes, 02/24/1944 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Text on folder "Proposed junior colleges for District of Columbia. Hospital plans"
  - Executive Committee--meeting minutes, 10/05/1943 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    Text on folder "Appointment of Miss Ruth Atwell as Activities Director. Authorization of President to proceed with Medical School survery."
  - Executive Committee--meeting minutes, 06/15/1943 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    Text on folder "Authorization of the President to sign the Army contract for the training of medical students. Discussion of the validity of contracts already made with the Government. Authorization of the President to borrow up to $10,000 to finance equipment for medical students."
  - Executive Committee--meeting minutes, 02/18/1943 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    Text on folder "Approval of awarding of certificates and conferring of degrees on February 22, 1943. New salary scale for employees at the Hospital. Authorization of President to proceed with erection of fire towers at the Hospital."
  - Executive Committee--meeting minutes, 08/06/1942 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    Text on folder "Manager for the Auditorium. Nurses' salaries. Wage schedules of janitorial, custodial, and engineering force. Management of the Hatchet. Vacation of Superintendent of Building Maintenance. Enrollment of Summer Session. Internal Revenue Service, Form 990. Bombing insurance. National Research Council--Professor Griggs."
  - Executive Committee--meeting minutes, 03/04/1942 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    Text on folder "Budget and financial outlook"
  - Executive Committee--meeting minutes, 01/20/1942 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    Text on folder "The Accelerated Academic Program. The Defense Alumni Council. The Division of Extension. Increase in salaries of employees. Retirement faculty."
  - Executive Committee--meeting minutes, 12/29/1941 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    Text on folder "The University and the Civilian Defense Program. Salaries of staff receiving less than $300"
  - Executive Committee--meeting minutes, 10/03/1941 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    Text on folder "Dormitory space for men. Madeira Apartments - 22d Street - Purchase"
  - Executive Committee--meeting minutes, 07/10/1941 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    Text on folder "Relationship with Corcoran Gallery of Art. Sale of Medical School property. Gift from Mellon Foundation. Report of Committee on Extracurricular Activities. Resignation of Professor Farrington. Appointment of Mr. Reinhart. Appointment of Mr. John Baker. Resignation of Associate Professor Bement. Discussion of Madeira Apartments property as possible men's dormitory. High School scholarships for Calvin Coolidge High School. Swisher Bequest. Question of increase in salary for Professor Wilgus. Communication from Health Security Administration. William B. King Bequest."
  - Executive Committee--meeting minutes, 04/29/1941 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Executive Committee--meeting minutes, 04/09/1941 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    Text on folder "Re: Personnel Committee. Extracurricular Activities Committee. Anuual Meeting"
  - Executive Committee--meeting minutes, 02/13/1941 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    Text on folder "Committee of Board on Administration of Prizes. Publicity Relationships. Sponsoring of D.C. Writers' Project. Change in Date of Annual Meeting"
  - Executive Committee--meeting minutes, 12/02/1940 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    Text on folder "Re: Prizes. Publicity. Group Hospitalization. Fire Requirements - Hospital. Defense Courses - Engineering. School of Public Affairs - American University"
  - Executive Committee--meeting minutes, 09/10/1940 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    Text on folder "Auditorium. Construction of Conduit. Operating Budget - 1939-40. Selective Service Law - (Prof. Ames). Personnel Committee of Board. Technical Training. Leave - Assistant Prof. Phillips"
  - Executive Committee--meeting minutes, 06/26/1939 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Executive Committee--meeting minutes, 04/19/1939 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Executive Committee--meeting minutes, 11/23/1938 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Executive Committee--meeting minutes, 07/15/1938 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Executive Committee--meeting minutes, 04/29/1938 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Executive Committee--meeting minutes, 01/26/1938 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Executive Committee--meeting minutes, 01/14/1938 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Executive Committee--meeting minutes, 02/17/1937 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    Text on folder "re: February 22, 1937 Convocation"
  - Executive Committee--meeting minutes, 02/17/1937 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    Text on folder "re: Feb. 22, 1937 Convocation"
  - Executive Committee--meeting minutes, 11/11/1936 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Executive Committee--meeting minutes, 05/20/1936 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    Text on folder "Housing. New Social Sciences Bldg"
  - Executive Committee--meeting minutes, 04/28/1936 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Executive Committee--meeting minutes, 04/21/1936 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Executive Committee--meeting minutes, 04/08/1936 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    Text on folder "Appointments - procedure to be used"
  - Executive Committee--meeting minutes, 03/17/1936 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Executive Committee--meeting minutes, 03/06/1936 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Executive Committee--meeting minutes, 12/06/1935 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Executive Committee--meeting minutes, 06/12/1935 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Executive Committee--meeting minutes, 04/02/1935 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    Text on folder "Re: Rockefeller Grant. Stike Against War. Etc."
  - Executive Committee--meeting minutes, 09/21/1934 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Executive Committee--meeting minutes, 01/17/1934 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    Text on folder "Sale of Treasury bonds, a part of Pairo Estate"
  - Executive Committee--meeting minutes, 01/17/1934 (Box 3, Folder 41)
    Text on folder "Re: Study of University Hospital Situation"
  - Executive Committee--meeting minutes, 01/31/1933 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Executive Committee--meeting minutes, 01/21/1933 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    Text on folder "Re: Report of President on Medical School Situation"
  - Executive Committee--meeting minutes, 10/28/1932 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Executive Committee--meeting minutes, 09/1932 (Box 3, Folder 45)
    Text on folder "In Re: Registration. Fall Convocation. Military Dept., Med. Sch. Resolution Re: commercialism in the University"
  - Executive Committee--meeting minutes, 10/21/1931 (Box 3, Folder 46)
    Text on folder "Re: Degrees - October Convocation. Sale of Columbia Sand and Gravel Stock. Purchase of property at 713 & 717 - 21st Street"
  - Executive Committee--meeting minutes, 09/30/1931 (Box 3, Folder 47)
    Text on folder "Re: Attitude of Dr. Freach of Medical School"
  - Executive Committee--meeting minutes, 05/11/1931 (Box 3, Folder 48)
    Text on folder "re: Property next to Garfield Hospital (Reimbursing of Trustees for - ) Payment of Wardman Commission on sale of B St. Property."
  - Executive Committee--meeting minutes, 04/15/1931 (Box 3, Folder 49)
    Text on folder "re: Purchase of statue of George Washington. Resolution concerning abrogating of contract with Garfield Hospital."
  - Executive Committee--meeting minutes, 01/22/1931 (Box 3, Folder 50)
    Text on folder "Re: 1. Mr. Lawson to check real estate notes 2. Community Chest"
  - Executive Committee--meeting minutes, 12/11/1930 (Box 3, Folder 51)
    Text on folder "re: Purchase of Lambre House. Relationship between the University and the Public Library. The Consolidation of Executory Trust Funds (4). Disciplinary action regarding Mr. Shapiro, Mr. Klatzkin. Discussed sale of 13th & H Sts."
  - Executive Committee--meeting minutes, 10/21/1930 (Box 3, Folder 52)
    Text on folder "In Re: - Relations [with?] Council of Social Agencies. Purchase of properties 25, 26"
  - Executive Committee--meeting minutes, 03/15/1930 (Box 3, Folder 53)
    Text on folder "Re: Hospital staff. Status of University under contract with Garfield"
  - Executive Committee--meeting minutes, 02/23/1930 (Box 3, Folder 54)
    Text on folder "Re: - Conferring of Degrees"
  - Executive Committee--meeting minutes, 01/24/1930 (Box 3, Folder 55)
    Text on folder "Re: Disposition of frame building on 718 - 20th Street. Discussion of abrogation of Agreement with Garfield Memorial Hospital. Admission of non-pay in Hospital to meet required number for approval of American Medical Association. Resignation of Dr. Randolph as Director of Clinics; appointment of Dr. Walter A. Bloedorn."
  - Executive Committee--meeting minutes, 06/09/1929 (Box 3, Folder 56)
    Text on folder "Re: Time of meeting. Appointment of Registrar. Report regarding the Two Hundredth Anniversary of the Birth of George Washington"
  - Executive Committee--meeting minutes, 06/04/1929 (Box 3, Folder 57)
    Text on folder "In Re: -1) Sale of B Street Property 2) Leave of absence - Mr. Jeuret"
  - Executive Committee--meeting minutes, 12/07/1928 (Box 3, Folder 58)
    Text on folder "Re: Budget Additions to Accounts #149 and #453. Approval of expenditure from Addie Sanders Trust Fund. Nurses' Home. Permit and custody of alcohol."
  - Executive Committee--meeting minutes, 01/05/1928 (Box 3, Folder 59)
    Text on folder "Re: President Marvin"
  - Executive Committee--meeting minutes, 10/06/1927 (Box 3, Folder 60)
    Text on folder "Re: Reorganization of University. Will of William D. Gardner"
  - Executive Committee--meeting minutes, 04/24/1911 (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - Executive and Finance Committee Joint Meeting--meeting minutes, 04/23/1953 (Box 3, Folder 62)
    Text on folder "Budget - 1954-55. Basis for budget 1954-55. Invitation permitting other than members to attend meetings of the Board"
  - Executive and Finance Committee Joint Meeting--meeting minutes, 03/11/1952 (Box 3, Folder 63)
    Text on folder "Hattie M. Strong Bequest - $15,000 endowment for the Hospital. John Sherba, student, wishes to appeal to Board. The Warwick Memorial Building - total grant from Public Health Service to be $200,000. G.W.U. Cancer Clinic - deficit might be between $30,000 and $70, 000. Committees voted for Board to proceed with erection of Warwick Memorial Building that President obtain pledged funds from the Washington Home for Foundlings and U.S.P.H.S., that ageement [agreement] be made with Charles H. Tompkins Co. for construction of Building, that land be transferred to Washington Home for Foundlings in accordance with agreement. that lease be obtained for building when completed, that President Marvin be given necessary powers to carry out all other terms of agreement. Remodeling of Building D. $289,000 required to remodel west half of building, to house Carnegie Library. Committees voted to proceed with the remodeling of Building D."
  - Executive and Finance Committee Joint Meeting--meeting minutes, 03/05/1952 (Box 3, Folder 64)
    Text on folder "Eugene and Agnes E. Meyer Foundation Scholarship. Remodeling of Building D. G.W.U. Cancer Clinic - total cost estimated at $80,000. Tax estimated at $12,000."
  - Executive and Finance Committee Joint Meeting--meeting minutes, 01/24/1952 (Box 3, Folder 65)
    Text on folder "Esther Brigham Fisher Fund for scholarships. Discussion of the resolution of the Association of American Law Schools re segregation. University's application for exemption denied on Lot 831 Square 41. President presented financial report upon the overall financing of University."
  - Executive and Finance Committee Joint Meeting--meeting minutes, 05/08/1951 (Box 3, Folder 66)
  - Executive and Finance Committee Joint Meeting--meeting minutes, 04/17/1951 (Box 3, Folder 67)
  - Executive and Finance Committee Joint Meeting--meeting minutes, 05/09/1946 (Box 3, Folder 68)
    Text on folder "The survey by the John Price Jones Corporation concerning the Hospital Equipment Drive"
  - Committee on Extracurricular Activities, Correspondence, 1941 -1956 (Box 3, Folder 69)
  - Committee on Extracurricular Activities--meeting minutes, 06/02/1961 (Box 3, Folder 70)
    Text on folder "Discussion re the agreement that the D.C. Armory Board has with the Washington Redskins concerning the use of the new Stadium. Discussion re the opening-day football game of the 1961 season. Recommendation that a plan for the field house be put "on paper". The meeting adjourned."